Hi all, good evening.
Give me a thumbs up if I'm audible and visible cool thank you guys hello so
we'll wait for some time today since it's a first class before I start
speaking on something I'll share my screen meanwhile so can you see my screen
share also so I'll keep the five minutes timers as that will start with the
content post five minutes meanwhile if someone want to talk about anything or
do you have anything we can discuss among among us okay so how's everyone
class strength I'm not sure I've enough have to check on that but currently I
see 15 people are there in the class so we'll wait for some more time and get to
know okay so how how is your preparation with our DSA and sequel do you feel
confident how many of you have cleared mock interviews for them or attempted
pretty good great little little good so how many of you are freshers if you are
give me thumbs up for the freshers
I'm due to job okay most excited for efforts great great okay I see six
people which I can say 25% of batches freshers cool since full stack is a
beginner course right for the it's designed for religion for freshers
perspective and we'll slowly speed it up do we cover react and Redux also yes
I've been I will cover that but it will come in the later part of the you know
curriculum initially we'll pick it up slow but slowly one after the other so
once we reach at good pace then we'll cover react Redux and other state
management tools and node express all things a complete monstack okay so we'll
wait for another three minutes you only take over the LDF here after yes I'll be
here Emma okay so I'll be helping you out okay my LinkedIn introduce myself
then I thought to share it give me a second I'll pull it up okay and what's
up group yeah I just want to create give me a second meanwhile when since we have
two minutes I'll create a whatsapp group for us
just a second till it loads I have to scan this
okay device
creating whatsapp group guys just a second
group so let's say
let me do one thing I'll create it in the break and I'll give it with you I'll
give to you okay so do we go into deep dive in each points of this module or
will go into deep dive permission so we'll build projects over the each module
if you learn react how much different is difficult angular to adopt so I'll tell
you on that part I'll come to that part frameworks are really after right so
just focus on basics once you build that I'll tell you how it is different and
what you need to learn okay you know so let's not jump into that depth like many
people might not know might have heard words like angular and react but they
might not know everything okay so I see we have good enough people today to get
started let me stop this timer and let's get started with the class okay give me
a second I hope you can see my iPad too
great so how's the juice guys give me a thumbs up if you can get started with
full stack LLD month stack right hi thank you so okay so firstly I want to
introduce myself so I'm Uttam Sharma right so I carry more than four point
seven years of work X working at PayPal since 1.5 years as SD 2 okay previously
I worked with UHG and HCL 2 that had really less amount of time spent here so
more on a PayPal basis so I've been a full stack developer since start of my
career with major centric focus centric was on front end and I had good
experience on node and Java stack to up to an extent on a back end and a middle
but major was on front end okay so this is just a introduction about myself so
this is what I've been doing or what what my experience is about but now let's
get started with today's content okay so firstly since it's a first class we'll
talk some some about like you know or something about web fundamentals
firstly once we cover what fundamentals will go for the introduction of HTML and
the thing okay so let's start with one of the basic questions okay one of the
basics questions that you come across okay like what do you think you know
when I go when I say let's say consider this will can start with the overview of
full stack how many of you understand what is full stack so how many of you
understand what is full stack okay front end place back end okay I see two
thumbs up two thumbs down maybe if it is more reactive right like let's keep
people if you can react thumbs up thumbs down maybe more okay I see many
of the people are you know giving me this answer which whether whether say
this is a front end plus back end okay it's equivalent to full stack so how
many of you agree with this which is friend and just back end is equal to
full stack right great so full stack is someone who knows end-to-end domain guys
who knows end-to-end domain so this is what they are trying to define it here
but let me you know not talking about technical let's pick up an example and
try to understand what full stack is okay so how many of you have been to
restaurants like many restaurants is taste like you been visiting right you
might everyone might in the class have been visited restaurant anytime in the
life right so can anyone help me out like what is once you go to go to
restaurant what things happen what are the events that happens in the
restaurants what are things are there like let's say this is a restaurant you
let's say let me draw a box here
okay so what all things can be there in a restaurant let's say this is a
restaurant so do we see a kitchen can there be a kitchen and restaurant table
chairs fine let's say this is our table and where you have many people sitting
over here okay and there can be a kitchen to write and fan AC menu all
this fine but now let's say when you go to the restaurant what we go for we go
for a lunch or the dinner or anything right so let's say consider we are the
people who are going to the restaurant to utilize its services okay once we are
going there there's a one person who comes and shows us menu who is that
waitress or waiter right let's say I'll turn down this thing waiter okay then
one is one is a person like let's say I write it down here so these are we
people who are visiting restaurant then we can say there's a waiter and waiter
brings us and gives us menu and what we do what we do then what we do then
once the waiter gives us menu we select and order it right we select and order
it once we select and order it then what waiter does then what waiter does once
we select and give it order what he do bring the food right so for bringing the
food he places an order into the kitchen right let's say this is a kitchen okay
so he sends an order and this you know what he brings back his food and this
food is actually served to us this is what the cycle is right the food is
served here isn't it this is what happens in restaurant do you guys agree
with this example at least like a simple example now let's say if I say
that under we if I put it this as a client
and under kitchen if I put it as a backend okay let's say something that is
transferring data or a waiter can be the HTTP protocols or HTTP has a DBS
protocols okay so I am what I'm saying is something that we are using it
utilizing it when I say client we can consider an example of mobile or desktop
or laptop any sort of this interfaces right whatever you see on screen that is
called a client which is interacting let's say we went to the restaurant and
we saw we sat down we are trying to utilize the services but we are saying
that hey I need this particular thing but we don't know how he's going to cook
it in kitchen isn't it we don't know how is going to cook it kitchen in kitchen
did he already prepared it or not or how we are going to get it but then there is
something called backend in backend you have something called servers okay this
is where kitchen kitchen lies so in backend you have two parts one is
application code then there is a databases okay now what happens in
application code let's consider this in the kitchen as a fridge or storage where
have groceries where you have everything put up like maybe cereals pulses rice
and everything you use this items and you cook it in an application code and
then you give it back the data to the client to show it onto the screen okay
now this communication whatever things are happening here now if you are
handling all the task right can the task of you know serving a customer could be
a waiter job which is actually related to the client and then which is a
cooking where you are trying to cook the items or like you know we're cooking it
like maybe anything that you order so that back-end job if you're handling all
these three jobs is generally called as full stack
is this a better way to understand it do you guys agree with me if you can
understand this or relate this now if someone asked about you know full stack
development now you can see that hey there is someone who is serving someone
serving us that's a client right like that's something like being served then
you have a back-end system like a kitchen where it's being cooked but we
don't know how it is being cooked it's something hiding behind us so these are
the machines which you cannot see it but these machines like the interface that
you are seeing like if you see on a scaler you are able to see me website I'm
able to screen share it we know that this is being done on the back end the
servers of scaler are trying to you know stream the data of my me being teaching
you are you learning from whatever I'm trying to teach that are happening on
the back end which we don't know how it is happening but just happening those
systems are there now so this is just an overview of how you know friend how
these things are connected when you when we say front-end exactly what we mean by
that is something our development which you are trying to do it on a client
side when I say client side basically all the devices in world it can be an
Apple watch it can be a smaller device to like bigger 65 inch screens okay
whatever it is whichever software it can be an Android iOS or web browsers or
anything whatever a end customer is experiencing so that customer
experiences built by a front-end which is done on the client side okay on back
end the scope is very huge which is server side are generally who handles
business logics mainly when I say business logic just a word keep it that
way that someone is cooking food for us we don't know how he is doing is
managing all things food is serving waiter is only handling the data which is
given by the kitchen or the chef so he's not responsible to cook it he
doesn't know what ingredients needed to cook it all things are done on
server side so main logic happens on the server side client side job is only to
you know present it communicate it well well like you know giving making it
descriptive good experience for the user okay I hope now front-end and back-end
idea is clear like what these are basically about and how we can
categorize them and how you can you know think of it as an example okay so if
this is clear can we go move ahead is good so let's get start with the second
thing okay so now there's a one interesting question guys I have one of
the interesting question that you should think of like you know when I say like
let's say let's say if I coin it this way what happens
when you enter URL in browser okay so just think of it like what happens when
you enter anything let's say you are trying to do scalar dot com okay just
something that you have been doing it every day or let's say few days back you
might have watched World Cup so you might have been checking that you know
scores of cricket matches okay so you know I'll try to write down all the
suggestions that are coming to me Teja and somebody it would be good if you can
bring it to the you know normal people not to me personally like everyone not
to the normal people I mean to say it will be helpful okay so it will direct
web page so one of the suggestion is that it loads the web page
second thing is request goes to DNS any more ideas guys what happens like let's
say when you enter scalar dot com actually what would actually what's
happening behind the scene think in terms of like the analogy in client or
desktop or the laptop you just enter a scalar dot com there is someone
picking up sign building it interface and giving back to us right someone is
doing it for us it will connect to scalar servers Dom okay it will fetch
the data from the server then it will show us on the web cool okay so a few
things that unique names I'm trying to I'll write it down they are says Dom
scalar servers okay okay cool now guys so let's say now you being here let's
say I'm taking this example as Teja is trying to search something in the
browser okay scalar dot com so we know commonly as an end user is something
that we are able to open dashboard right we are able to open dashboard and we
know that once dashboard is so we know that there's something being received so
somebody is cooking us that website and giving us back okay somebody is doing
this thing at least everyone agrees with this right we are entering scalar dot
com it is authenticating if user is logged in we are getting a dashboard of
our acts right this thing is clear now but we'll understand what all steps are
it's going through in the back end how it is you know trying to get it now tell
me something scalar dot com so one thing we are sure about is this front end or
back end everything is in computer isn't it your mobile isn't computer your
laptops are computer back end servers are also computer isn't it now if that's
so how does the scalar dot com or the browser knows to go which way to go out
to reach out to which computer that will give it resource I mean how do you know
that how does chrome or any browser knows that when I type search a scalar
dot com here I should go to a particular computer and fetch the data so people
are saying IP okay by IP address anyone else anyone else URL is basically an IP
DNS server okay DNS server cool so guys let's take an example of phone book
right let's say I want to make your call let's say I want to make let's say you
are trying to make a call to your friend you don't remember numbers of
friends right all friends what do you do once you open the mobile what do you
usually do what is the approach that you follow you go and type the name right
you go and search and type the name and you directly click on a call button
right so can you can you think of this way it is a map of string and string or
a number where you are storing let's say my name and xxx right this is how your
phone book is stored you click on its number and dials up right now everyone
is saying that you know all the websites in this world are known by phone numbers
now like their numbers they have specific unique coding okay whenever you
type down scalar dot com okay scalar doesn't know this particular name right
domain name or the website name doesn't know which system it need to contact it
but there is a one system which maintains this mapping this map mapping
like which which stores that hey if someone is typing scalar right I have to
give it back some number of system like that could be a ten dot eleven dot one
twenty seven dot something something zero okay so there is a one system which
keeps all the mapping among of the all the websites in the world could be
google.com or could be any website any other websites okay they all maintain a
mapping table okay this particular machines right hope the stores this data
are known as DNS machines or you can say domain name system
okay so as you make a phone call yeah we'll come to that so as you make a phone
call you try to go and search in the contact list right hey I want to dial
this person now similarly in any website or anything in the browser whenever you
try to make a call to a particular website it's just like a phone call okay
so what it goes is talk to this machine hey can you give me the phone number of
this particular website no this particular website gives us back this
ID or you can say IP address of that machine and port number port number
could be four digit once it have this IP right or you can say public IP of a
machine then it goes and reach out to the backend system
this logic is clear guys firstly at least like there is a some machine
called DNS domain names system server which is maintaining whole mapping of
our you know phone numbers or the IP addresses for the each name that you
type it okay so now this is there you know before even going to the reaching
out this backend server right there are many steps that
intermediately happens there are many things that happen now imagine you type
in your browser a new website name compared to something that you keep
visiting imagine you go into incognito not an incognito window but a new system
and a new place you type down scalar.com if scalar.com a new let's say you
type it down and if it is taking let's say 10 seconds okay but if you type it
on in your system it might take only two to three seconds okay so if if what I
mean to say is that this is like first time visiting
this is from the second or nth time visiting the website so what I mean to
say is that when you visit a website for the first time right it is taking long
amount of time but when you're visiting from the second time to the nth time it
generally takes less amount of time have anyone felt this way earlier in
life or whenever you have seen this okay when you type something new right takes
time to load compared to yeah it stores right okay now so why this happens
we'll try to understand reasons behind this okay how many of you know heard
this word called cache how many of you know this word cache anyone who haven't
heard it I see 13 people cool now what happens right okay so you know there are
multi-level of caching that happens multi-level now we'll try to see what
levels of caching in generally happens with respect to this DNS map okay no so
first when we type in browser a new website at scalar comm first it where it
goes it goes to it try to search in browser cache just a second this
you
pardon me guys my niece was inside the room so I have to ask her to go out so
okay coming back to the topic so whenever you search scalar comm inside
the website right it goes and try to see in the browser cache when I say browser
cache cache is nothing but a memory a temporary memory okay so this browser
engines right whatever you say chrome or edge or anything everyone stores this
mapping whatever key value pair mapping of a particular site name a domain name
and IP addresses okay where actual servers are residing where I have tried
to reach it up okay so this first level of caching is stored in the browser
level once the browser level if when we are trying to do scalar comm checks in
the browser cache that if it is there that's fine if it is not there then it
will go to the next level what would be what do you think in terms of internet
where it should go to the next level DNS directly no there are multiple other
stages the rich think of it from computer whenever you're trying inside
the browser where this browser is running on where this browser usually
runs on on what type of machine this browser PC right how this species running
how what is driven driven on PC operating system right OS so then there
is something called OS cache so there can be a chance if if not in the browser
cache because that there might be a chance right you might search scalar
comm in chrome tomorrow you might not like the chrome you might open in the
edge okay first it will go to scalar from scalar to browser it didn't find it
it will go at the OS level it knows the mapping it will be this OS cache will
return that you know IP address of machine and it will go and reach it out
this is point here so once OS cache is clear think of it where it can go
further
there's a one level of it then it goes through DNS let's say I'll write down
here as one level and then from here it goes to DNS think of it where it can go
in between
anyone in the class
route okay anyone else shake is actually right so we say that ISP is right
internet service providers whoever is providing us internet like could be an
atl or geo or you can say act fibernet or multiple people who are providing us
so this particular ISP's firstly there's a router at your home right in your
router machines that you have a box which provides you the Wi-Fi so even
that Wi-Fi box right it is also storing some data that shows it store this
cache like of the website or the IP address mapping if it is not there in
cache then it goes to ISP then if internet service providers also not
having it's it's a new URL new website that got added into DNS then it goes to
DNS then on reverse right once it is reaching out on the back end it goes to
each step and it stores that key value mapping at each step okay then it gives
us back this particular IP address is this point here guys at least like
anyone having any doubts on this like how we are able to get the IP address or
you can say a phone number sort of logic of a back-end server where it is located
okay or you can say where kitchen is there who is giving us the scalar dot
com dashboard okay so I'll write down this step as a simple way let's say this
is a client okay let's try to reach out multiple systems okay so let's say first
step is browser cache then it goes to OS then it goes to a router then ISP then
DNS so what it returns us overall is the IP address IP address of server so once
it has IP address of server it goes and interacts to the server okay this server
might be returning us HTML website yeah we can see this in live I'll show it
give me a second okay so this server is returning us HTML data or any other
format data router is your Wi-Fi box right which is you are having in the
home okay that is what now once you have this right once you have this IP address
it goes to the server server let's say let's keep it this whole thing right
what's happening here behind the scene how it is interacting with DB and what
it is happening how the communication between these two things are happening
let's keep it as a black box as of now because we'll explore this once we
start with a back-end system but let's understand till here like this
interaction till this interaction okay this interaction okay so now we say that
I mean let's see this let's see this in life let me open the browser let me try
to let's say any famous websites that you want to open or you want to open
itself okay let's open the scalar.com itself okay scalar.com if you see you
know scalar.com slash Academy mentis dashboard there's something that
happened okay now if you see we got the dashboard completely I hope you can see
the screen right I hope you can see the screen all of you okay great so now if
you see here below there are too many API calls are being done you know if you
see this fetch call okay initial load data or user info let's say I'm trying
to fetch the user info details of all these things are being merged to get the
data but we'll see each one step by step now if you see here okay here request
URL is www.scalar.com slash user info but the remote address is this one can you
see this IP address
so this one is a machine which will give me this user info data so this is what
I was talking about this particular mapping right to this website slash user
info need to be fetched from this particular site is being stored okay now
if you see all the things right remote if you see 13.35 point like 21056
443 now 443 is a port number if you if I go and open all the webs all the API
calls I'm trying to interact with only one machine if you say 443 all the way
although you know this remote addresses are same but if you come and see this
one right again there is something new thing that is being fetched it is
interacting with different system okay so all the things if you see there are
different things are being you know taken into accordance to build this
particular screen that you see here but all the data that you see are being
fetched from a server a different location there's a machine which is
kept there and from using that we are able to load it okay now if I show you
one of the thing let's say this are fetch xx hr let's say document okay okay
if you see it here so now this is the actual website you know menti dashboard
you can see this menti dashboard slash to dos which is the actual URL that we
hit now this mentis dashboard is you know we are hitting still on the same
machine that is being reverted with you know HTML I'll come to this what it is
this HTML or what what we are talking about I'll introduce this properly but
this is something a response like when we order a food from the kitchen waiter
is bringing us something back food now this is the food which is given to the
browser back and this thing is being understood by the browser and being
loaded this point is clear guys how this interaction is happening where that
systems are located or what this for remote rather scale multiple servers
yeah there will be a different things right so this like you have you can have
a number of machines you go for the bigger sites they'll have the different
contents if you know when you go for Microsoft is sort of architecture each
service will be doing some sort of work so you will be able to see the different
addresses okay but overall the core logic is that there's a client which
don't know anything we just say that scalar.com I didn't say that hey go and
interact with a ten dot twenty one dot two zero five dot four four three system
or any other machine I've just that scalar.com it automatically handled
figured out where to fetch and what what need to fetch if you see it happened at
so pace that it took more less than ten seconds or less than three seconds of
time to fetch all the data and load it okay I hope now you feel I mean I'm
having a better idea of like actually what's happening isn't it like how this
data is being fetched on to the client or which machine or how machine is
generally interacting how clients are interacting with the machines which are
somewhere present we don't know right anyone having any doubts till now what
we have discussed okay now no let's say you know we'll talk about something
called just and this is an overview guys don't be overwhelmed if you are not
completely able to get it but they're really basics we'll discuss this over
over the time again and again to get complete clarity okay now so I said
that you know these are two machines which is client and server these two
people got the address now this machine got the address where this is located do
you think once I do this you know the server will give me the all the list of
resources it have if I go to any random restaurant and as I say that hey give me
a piece of biryani would they give it to me or it will give to a authorized
waiter itself it will give to an authorized person only know it should be
a like he should be having certain validations and things now before that
before going to that authentication authorization process there is a you
know to establish connection right to establish connection between client and
server in order to say that hey I'll keep exchanging this data once I have
hit you yeah I know your address I came to your you know I came to your machine
now I want to make a connection with you so that I can keep exchanging resources
okay so for that thing there's a one type of connection which is
established which is called as TCP connection there are other types of
connections also which will you will learn in the high-level design course
but anyone have heard about this TCP connection earlier have anyone heard
about this okay I see four people three people some stuff okay no worries guys
so what happens in general right okay when clients client is there no where
there's let's say this is a client machine and this is a server machine
once you know the address once you know the address to the server right to
establish a connection you send a signal called acknowledge you send a machine
to the server called acknowledge signal so this is on a top level guys from you
can say 10,000 feet not into the complete depth because in complete
depth you'll learn again and the future HLD classes okay but what happens in the
does is when whenever you are trying to interact with any other system firstly
you will try to say validate yourself saying that acknowledgement let's say
I'm trying to come in me I'll say hello hi right now I'll say I'll extend my
hand and then say hello so that what this client machine does it says that
acknowledge it sends a signal called AK now if this person want to respond right
this person want to respond back then what it does is it says that sink it
with a smile then he also says that hello back again okay then if this
client if they're making a connection then it sends a third message called
sink which means you just remember this as a handshaking process this is called
three-way handshake generally
how connection is establishment to two machines let's say I go to I come to you
and I say that I'll hello when I extend my hand and saying hello if you like to
connect with me you'll also smile greet with greet me with smile and you will
also keep me back your hand shake hand saying hello isn't it and then if I
smile back then the connection is established for the further
conversation so far it starts with a greeting so you can understand this as
a three-way handshake where the greeting happens is this clear guys
anyone having any doubts so just remember this one as a top level anyone
have asking how TCP three-way handshake happens it's just a greetings is
extending a hand smiling if the other person also smile back then the
connection is established two things acknowledge and reverse acknowledges and
then there's a sink messages which happens okay clear I hope there are no
dodge so once the this this thing is happened right now all the data or the
network now this is what we call network okay there are two machines they are
somewhere located but if two people are interacting they interact over the
network now there is some person who will hold the load of communicating okay
what type of communication is happening which type of things are happening what
he is bringing or what he generally happening right for all those net what
communication that are happening with the network in order to understand you
use something called there are two types of protocol which is one is called HTTP
and the other one is called HTTPS this is a secured way this is a normal call
HTTP is a hypertext transfer protocol okay which are generally used for
transferring transferring the messages over the network okay is this clear on
a top level what is TCP connection and HTTP I mean I'm trying to generalize
such a way that you know you can understand connect with them not in
complete depth knowledge as a networking class since this is a full stack class
I'm just trying to okay I'll get to the full form I don't exactly remember
the agent let me fetch it TCP full form transmission control protocol okay it's
a transmission control protocol
then there is another another protocol called a UDP can you could you explain
the TCP purpose once again yeah sure Suresh so not going just as spending
another minute now let's say that hey what happened is you got the phone
number you picked it up from the mobile you searched it now we are trying to
click on it when you're trying to click on it there's the connections that
should be established between your mobile and your friends mobile right
which is your where you are trying to call now in order to make this call to
work then there is something called you know connection establishment does
happen between two missions okay so that connection establishment is in that for
establishing this connection there's a one type of condition that we generally
is TCP connection where you have this process of three-way handshake this
three-way handshake is specific to HTTP in HTTPS you have further because you
have to extend certificates and multiple things but just the knowledge that I'm
trying to explain the CCP connection is because I'm saying that hey once you got
the phone number you cannot make a direct call you need some network
connection which needs acknowledgement that hey I want to connect with this
particular person is that clear Suresh okay yeah there's a handshake is a like
one of the core thing without connection you cannot extend the network data over
the network right so that it will happen every time okay it will happen every
time but it takes a really less amount of time now moving right guys I hope
this thing is clear now just a second so coming back to HTTP and HTTPS no once
you have established connection there is a now you are once you establish a
connection you keep talking to your friend right you might speak in English
or Telugu or Hindi different languages do you guys agree you speak in a
communication language you have a language to speak with your friend now
imagine for this language right you have a particular protocol now those
protocols are defined by HTTP and HTTPS now for this one you have only four
things in general that are happening on a server either you are getting a data
hey you are asking like can you give me some information or you are yourself
giving some information which is a post call or you are saying that hey that
information which I gave earlier which was wrong so I'm trying to update that
information using put and then you say that hey can you please remove that
information which is not needed using delete so there are four types of
communication that happen generally between two machines these are the four
things to create a resource
okay sorry this is a get a resource or create a resource update a resource or
delete a resource right in general these are the four types of communication that
happens and these are being generally done from client client says that hey
can you give me because I made a communication network with you I called
you you have to serve my request so client make a request using this four
types of communication so it says to the HTTP that HTTP asked us to provide
which type of communication you need it whether you want to get some data or you
want to create a data or update data or delete data once your request is made
right server response back
back with some information no but there are multiple informations that are
happened transferred over the network I will discuss that about in depth later
on but what server responses response in terms of you know status quotes there
are many status quotes that you will see now if I show you one of the status
code that we have generally seen as of now if I go back into this website if
you see if I open anything if you see here 302 200 302 right a 304 all these
are status quotes these are being given by server now if you go back to headers
right here I'm saying that request method get so we are saying that hey I
made a communication with you I want to get the data now in the response if you
go to the response right here let's say response it is giving us 302
redirection I'll see I will talk about all the status quotes how in a top
level how the status code works let's say they are basically status quotes in
5 series 1 xx 2 xx 3 xx 4 xx 5 xx ok now one of the error code everyone knows is
404 not found right everyone knows this does everyone know this 404 error now
what this 404 error says what what this 404 errors mean is something that you
are trying to search or get the data it is not available let's say you give some
gibberish website let's say you give them some gibberish website let's say I
go and open a network tab and inspect it let's say I clean this I write
something okay and I try to search okay it's giving me something or that lot of
information available in Google but what happens is if there is nothing
available with this name or this thing right URL that there is no resource
available then what it says that hey you have made a mistake there is nothing a
place called this one or there is no mapping available where I have to route
machine okay so we say that client had made a mistake or you are pointing to
the wrong direction let's say you are going to Ambani and asking her to be to
cook a tea it's not possible man right so he wouldn't be available to do it for
you so that's not found resource not found he won't be able to serve you so
it's a your mistake that you're asking a wrong person to do something now if
something let's say you after four four xx series right you might have also
seen five excess series also have anyone faced 5x code series 500 server down
right people say that five server is down server is down what does it mean
what does it mean when I say server is done the back-end system right this
server the system is shut down internal server error okay bad bad gateway so all
these things all the 500x codes whatever you come see right those are like
problem with server like you don't know there is a issue with a server ongoing
so you cannot do anything so 4x series is something that you can't do right
this is something problem from the front-end 5x series is something a
problem from the back-end is this clear 4x and faxes might be clear right now
then there is something called 2x code so this is a success code for all the
get calls for all the get calls right you get a success code or the post calls
you get to 200 code or 202 code where you are trying to say that whatever you
want you made a request of these four items get post delete and if that
particular call whatever you request made it if it is successful it will
return us that data along with the status code of 200 okay then there is
something called three excess three excess is something like redirection just
we have seen is that if you see scalar.com got I just entered scalar.com
but it redirected me to menti dashboard have you seen this I have entered
scalar.com only but it took me to the menti dashboard right URL got appended
dynamically it's a runtime and it loaded me a new site instead of loading just a
scalar.com
did you guys notice that or I'll show it again okay I'll show it again if you
need give me a second
let's clean it up again let's say scalar.com let's say I'm just entering
scalar.com when I click enter if you see it appended menti dashboard and to dos
now why this happened is it says that scalar.com by default home page is not
available it need to someone hitting this URL need to be navigated to menti
dashboard now but if you see when I hit a scalar.com it is giving me 300 status
code it means it's saying that hey this something I recognize it but actual
website where you have to go to is menti dashboard so whenever something is
coming with a 300 X code return return status right response status it is
something related to
redirection
okay and there is one thing which is left is info first one excess code
whenever you see this is one of the rare code it gives just the information
okay information about resource
I've seen very rare use case of 1x code which you might not have face it but it
gives just gives information about resources like back-end system and where
it is and if you want to fetch information about systems okay and that's
not commonly used mainly important things that you need to remember is 2x
4x and 5x okay whatever this code starts with 2 4 and 5 are more important 2
stands for success 4 stands for client-side mistake 5 stands for server
side mistake okay now I hope this part is clear like how when I said that I
just want to focus on this part layer till this part okay so firstly if I try
to repeat this revise this once okay what we thought what we okay 1x code
okay let's say I try to give an example of 1x code let's say
just a second I'll fetch it and show you what actually gives us okay so here
they say is that you know information response now what sort of information
responses like you know in on the network layer like switching protocols
are processing this is not actually used on the system like I we don't really use
them when you're developing websites or applications you never throw 1x code
this is actually happened on a network layer by the systems itself that
servers that handle where it shares shares information about the resource
let's say client machine resource the what this client machine is all about
what this server machine is all about okay you won't be able to see it in the
network because whatever you make either whenever you making a yeah I'll give you
the real-time scenario for 1x code give me some time but what I was trying to
say talk about is when when communication is happening between two
system right if you think it from the perspective of communication is
happening firstly either this person can say wrong or either this person can say
wrong or this person both can you know like make a communication real real you
know work properly so if this person is making wrong it is 4x code if this
person is making wrong this is 5x code and if there is something going right
between all the communication then there is a 2x code okay for 1x I'll get I'll
get the real-time examples I'll share it with you okay works guys okay cool now
trying to revise again repeat once on a top level so then we have understood
that what happens in the browser whenever you enter a URL so the first
thing that we have figured out that when on the client whenever you enter
anything it goes to you know a series of steps okay I'm wrong with spellings
series series of steps no to fetch IP address of server once it gets IP address
it goes to the server but no there are two things that are happening in middle
one is connection TCP connection this thing we have learned two things three
things happen in the ACP handshake ACK where it sends some client to server and
server sends sync less ACK then client again says sync okay once this
connection is done then this people connect and communicate using HTTP
protocols
I hope now you are at least on a top level you have a you know greater
clarity what is happening behind the scenes how data is being served from a
machine right this is clear guys okay if there are other than any doubts other
than one excess please shoot it I'll wait for a minute to before I go ahead
because next topic that something that I want we need to get started with is
introduction to HTML part because this is you know high-level introduction
about web fundamentals where we understood about what full stack domain
is overall like what what we have what we have to work or what we have to learn
then we understood like what happens in a system actually when you enter any you
are this things acts as a base to move ahead in the further classes okay this
was being a theoretical now we'll start with a more practical part so as height
when API comes into the picture okay now okay
API's are generally let's say
I'm a client I'm a server okay a client can talk to multiple people
okay let's say how do I say okay this way
yes yes this day right so API's are application programming interface they
say that you know these are the end points with which you can connect to
get the information that you want now this like you know using this whatever
get post delete calls right you cannot say that randomly give me any
information for getting this information this server should support right firstly
back-end system should support that hey you can get this information from me I
can give you this information now to get that you know in order to give that
information right this back-end systems build application programming interface
there can be multiple endpoints like we have seen one of the end point is user
info when we entered you know scalar comm right we seen that user info now
user info is a get call now how we know that we ensure interact user info will
get the data because inside the server they are someone who is listening to get
call on this URL called user info so someone is coming with you know this
call then they'll do something they'll implement some logic and give it back to
us now this endpoints right whoever are building this in points like the URL
pattern or the type of HTTP methods who are defining it if you particularly hit
this particular thing you will be able to do this let's say if you go for again
restaurant right there can be Chinese restaurant there can be a South
Indian restaurant there can be Japanese restaurant where you can eat sushi
American and South Indian you can eat South Indian breakfast so if you go for
one particular sort of restaurant you can get only particular item you cannot
get the other items so now each server will have a capability to serve
particular things now all those capabilities are defined by using this
menu now well waiter is bringing us menu now we know that what all things it can
give it us those menu items are only API's is that clear Sean the that menu
items right whatever API's are being developed in the back end are the menu
items now we select those many items like the user info get for this
particular server and we try to interact with them so that generally the menu you
can consider example as a menu or the API's okay now yeah I hope I hope this
this top level this thing is clear but this way this will be coming back to us
again and again when while we are discussing a whole end to end right
TCP call is made with which server TCP call is made with the actual server
which where you are trying to fetch the IP address once you receive an IP address
from the beginners right that a particular IP address whichever mission
is mapped to it will try to establish a connection with that let's say I got a
phone number of you Suresh from my dialer I try to make a call I'm trying
to establish connection with you with your server with your mobile phone
that's what is happening here is that here so nice so guys moving it from
here now now is actually where we start with HTML okay how many of you are
completely beginner to this word HTML how many of you are completely beginner
to this word HTML
please what it guys it will it will allow me to know if I can go speed or
slow or what pace I will maintain it okay cool I didn't get your point
Muneshwara beginner okay no worries okay cool so I see you guys 50-50 ratio
people there too many beginners so we'll start with completely basic people who
already know people who already know right 12 people I would ask you to you
know have some patience till I build the basics but all the people are starting
from zero such that we'll bring him on to the pace and then we'll continue
from there okay great now so let's take an example you know so I'll introduce
three words now let's not introduce HTML let's take an example of
building a house
now tell me what all three things that are happened like when you build an
house let's say imagine building an house so I'm asking for all the nine
like you know people who haven't doesn't know anything or who knows everything
doesn't matter but just tell me what happens what are the events that are
there while building a house
basement cool plan layout plan cool basement pillar walls right cool yeah
let's say I'm building a two-story house plan is ready everything is ready okay
foundation column beams okay foundation
columns and beams now let's say this is done then then what you do okay someone
says structure okay one structure is done what do you do can you go and stay
in a house which is structured okay roof is added here itself
bricks cement now yeah there's something called paint interior now let's say paint
and interior is done tiles are done foundation roof columns are beams are
done now what would be other thing what you would have
plumbing electricity okay
cool guys thank you so much you have solved my problem actually now let's
try to connect this root dots okay let's get it this starts so now even while
building websites you need all of these things you need all of these things so
what if I put this all these things let's say a roof basement walls floor
everything into a structure structure of a building is this clear do you agree
with me if I can put all of them into this category structure of a building
right now second thing would be painting a house or adding an interior so what
we are doing we are making it to look beautiful
beautifying the house beautifying the structure I can say isn't it right now
once these two things are done then there is something someone say that
plumbing plumbing or electricity okay or you can say fan you know lights or
anything now what these are giving us this this thing is giving us you know
behavior let's say I'm going on switching on a fan when I click a
button is something rotating right isn't it something rotating when we switch on
the fan there's something rotating or there's a light on that's what behavior
is happening right even in the website you go and see a website you scroll it
down where only when you scroll that page goes up or you click a button there
is something happening isn't it same as a like something happening on the house
interaction or clicking button presses clicks or let's say clicks interaction
okay so these three things are happening in the website too we are building a
structure of a website we are making it look beautiful using adding colors we
are adding behaviors like you know behaviors like as you're giving me
typing it down you're posting it so all these are behaviors so all these three
things are need to be handled whenever you are building this website okay so
for building doing each of this work right since these three are core
fundamentals of any building there are you know there these three things are
really important in order to be good at web development so now let's say the
first point whatever you say the structure of building I categorize as
HTML now when I want to color a building or add a more beautification part I say
it is a CSS then there is something called electricity or you know lights or
I want to say that hey someone clicked button I want to fit some data or like
you go on a Netflix you click a movie button watch now it loads a movie there's
something who is getting the data for us loading that movie so that thing's
behavior can be handled using JS is that clear guys on top level what HTML CSS
or JS is behaviors only that roles of them okay I've took an example of house
I hope you never forget it and now one tricky question I want to ask everyone
how many of you think HTML and CSS are programming languages how many of you
think HTML and CSS are programming language
okay so I have four people saying yes guys so firstly they're not okay because
one thing I'll tell you programming language is handling only behavior part
behavior part when I say behavior part what I exactly meant is something
someone is user reacting to clicks or building the data or someone cooking it
or anything something which is really static doesn't have any programming to
be written you cannot write for loops while loops or additions or any
arithmetic operation
using this tool so never say whenever you're saying that HTML and CSS you
cannot use them for you know as a calling them as a programming language
there's a difference why when we say that's a programming language you can do
all the problem-solving events now HTML CSS are solving different problems but
the actual when we say that a high-level programming language those are something
that you apply you know too much of logic to build something like you said
DSA you're solving a problem statements for them those sort of things like when
you're trying to solve those are problems there you have like language
like JS Java Python okay these are the high-level programming language you have
many Ruby go lang okay no JS there are too many things okay but HTML and CSS
are not a programming I'll explain more reasoning for this but on top level at
this point they are not programming language only the reason is you cannot
write for loop and while loop and no problem can be solved without adding a
loops or recursion logic isn't it can you solve any DSA problem without
writing a loops or a recursion you pick it up any data structure you pick it up
any data structure you pick it up anything you won't be able to solve it
so now this is just an top level guys never say that it's a programming
language now we'll start with official introduction of HTML okay let's say we
are starting with HTML if I write down the full form of this one right we call
it as hypertext markup language okay so we'll come to this definition step by
step okay we'll come to this definition step by step you need a break can we
take it after 15 minutes have you know works at 130 hours like class of 130
hours okay cool now in this HTML there are only two things right if you if you
learn two things right if you learn only two things that's enough if you learn
only two things that's enough to you know you will figure it out all the
other things you'll figure it all the other things now what are those things
are two things are some says element some says tax this is one thing second
thing is called attributes or some says properties these are the only two things
present in a HTML whenever you write now to design any structure of a website
right content you have only these two things elements and tax have anyone
heard of this things attributes elements and tax earlier can anyone give me an
example of element or tag
someone says P okay good good good okay so let me dive down this one button as
people can understand image okay anchor I'm writing down things only which I'll
introduce now okay paragraph heading these are the elements or tax what are
the attributes are the properties
what are the attributes are the properties okay source or href okay
anything else guys does anyone remember
iframe is again a different thing big thing so someone says hash ID but it is
only an ID then there is something called class name class then there's
something called style right all these are attributes okay now for the people
who are completely picked us right understand this one elements are
something which is you to add a structure to a website these are the
things which are adding a structure elements can be anything could be an
button button now to define an element you use this way there is an a button
once you define this way okay this is an element can be a button to click okay you
define an element this way an element is something which has a opening and a
closing okay something which is born it will surely die okay once you define an
element you can write the content it will see this in live after the break
but on a top level elements and attributes are only the things which can
which can be used to define the whole HTML content all the now will see them
live but attributes are something which is used to enhance property of element
applied on it okay let's say you have defined a button there are too many
buttons buttons will have a color or you can add a style button you want to make
the button to look in a different way or the button should be jumping all of them
can be done using attributes you have to define different attributes okay this is
on a top level what elements and attributes are I hope this is clear
anyone having any doubts on that on this we'll see them in live again once
we start coding we'll start coding in the you know ten minutes later but
anyone having any doubts on this on this like elements and attributes I hope no
right class will go till 11 yeah yeah we will be going till 11 okay so I hope
there are no doubts now since I have four five minutes I'll explain what is
you know this HTML is you know markup whenever someone says that you know
markup language so it means to say that structure structure website you can take
the example as something adding a structure to it you have anyone have
written anything in the life called readme.md files have anyone written
readme.md files in life earlier markdown files okay no I'll show you that one how
we do it but all the markdowns right markdown files or markup files are
generally adding a structure to the content now wherever you use this word
called markup it is just adding a structure to a particular thing that's
where these people used as a markup okay now second thing they use something
called hypertext they use something called hypertext
when I say hypertext I mean to say that do you know have you seen XML comes
under markup language not exactly Suresh not exactly okay markup is
something different XML is different okay I mean it can be a part of a
category out out of that but I'll try to you know Google and come back to that
exactly okay but now coming back to hypertext if you see in websites right
you have many things like buttons you can see something which is like a links
you can see right there are too many links on a website or even if you
prepare a resume who have built it you might have added a scalar you know
your coding profile you might have added your github profile you might have given
your you know LinkedIn right have you have have you prepared anyone have
prepared the resumes adding these three links at least right now these are the
links that are done now imagine this links once you click a link you are
redirected to that particular website right could be a github or scalar or
lead code or whatever you have a github now this redirection is able to happen
because they are hypertext then when we say that their hypertext we mean to say
that hyper linking hyperlinking of text so the text is up entry point which is
redirecting you to the next something new place so that's why we say that is
a hyper linking of text which is helped to structure a website now even if your
resume is something called a HTML only which doesn't have color or which is
normal in different fonts different typography and just you having a
hyperlinks are able to relate now definition of HTML also because that's a
bookish definition it doesn't really matter to us now if we have once we have
understood this book is definition right not needed but the way I understand the
way I understand is HTML is mother tongue
to browse
why do I say mother tongue to the browser is because imagine we have each
person is very much comfortable with their mother tongue right because there
is something that you have learned in the while you were born first isn't it
you might be super comfortable because you've learned it at home and you
understood it you know that's really easy to understand and you know do it
sometimes what happens is people who are trying to learn new language let's say
if someone is trying to learn maybe someone who moved from North India to
South India is trying to understand small words he tried to relate those
words convert into their mother tongue and try to connect a dot if someone is
saying something right do you guys agree with me let's say someone is coming from
Delhi Delhi to Hyderabad someone is speaking in Telugu okay and his mother
tongue person who is in Delhi his mother tongue is Hindi and he came here he is
trying to learn Telugu so first thing he'll learn is like I'm a Telugu I know
Telugu so first thing he'll learn is like I don't know Telugu right can you
speak in Hindi this is our English he'll say this line so whenever you teach him
that person right hey I don't know Telugu can you like can you speak in English or in Hindi
so if you I have sprained the sentence now but whenever happens
whenever a new person comes in whenever I say this thing he tried to map this
each letter in Hindi back right he's trying to convert back into mother
language and then understand it and remember it you guys agree this is a
process generally what we follow if you are trying to learn something new right
so even in the browser right even in the browser it is same thing for browser
browser can understand something is HTML by this is his mother language if you
give him this data it will load the website at a short it didn't need to
translate or convert into anything it will load it a short so if you see even
when we loaded a scalar website first okay something that we got in the
initial response was HTML all the other things if you see other things all the
other things were you know script JavaScript is downloaded later on but
first HTML was loaded this is something a browser understands once we load this
if you see the like if you say this is a title that scalar is coming now the
title will be if I hover over it
okay home scalar everything you will be able to find how it is happening okay so
but I hope you are able to relate this this is a mother tongue of a browser
which it can understand it exactly and it is very speeded understanding it
doesn't need to go to multiple steps so if you are serving HTML to a browser
it's a cakewalk for it to load it fast but if you are giving a code or a logic
to run in the browser it takes time to convert into to what it understands it
then render it onto the screen okay I hope you are able to understand now what
HTML is basically on top level because this will help to understand the word
called Dom in the future classes I'll introduce Dom I'll see if I can
introduce today itself but okay I hope now you got that on a top level what
hypertext markup bookish examples you learn a lot but watch my idea is right
how I understood the computer scientists with my examples something
that I see in real life I go to the store and I try to connect with them I
try to see everywhere what is in general connected with the nature that we see so
that's that way if you try to remember will remember for life okay so the my
notes would be not that bookish all our notes or my way of teaching wouldn't be
that way it would be really simple on a top level so that it would be easy so
whatever code we write is converted into HTML completely no some bit no I'll come
to that wait for you know I would say two months actually when we come to
react you will be amazed how things are working okay but wait for some time
like but I'll you can ask me this thing again then but I'll show it but
understand this thing this is something that someone understands it HTML okay
browser understand this thing for sure so I hope the class you are clear with
the things till now you know what we have learned I hope if you are clear we
can go with the you know break session okay how many minutes of break you
usually want
how many minutes of break you needed five minutes would be fine right because
we have to cover some content since it's initial class okay I'll give the five
minutes guys to keep it in between okay let's reset this one and start it okay
so that we can end class early that's my point okay starting this timer
please take break guys see you in five minutes again
this Java is helpful for the full stack developers I'll answer you back to this
again in some time after a break
you
I hope everyone is back guys can anyone give me some sub-thumbs down if you are
back any reactions so guys should I have I've got nine responses so I'll take one
doubt that I had it there is what is a usage of one excess code I don't
remember who asked me but what is the use of one excess for an HTTP coach so
one excess is not an end state it is an ongoing state okay so whenever you make
a request and your response is served okay
response is being served it goes through multiple states like continue or
switching protocols
like this is no yeah so there is no like thing like what it is defining an
instant it is not really you won't be receiving the status code in your
request or the response it is just a happening at a network level that it is
saying that what are the steps are happening at that time I was taking one
doubt some bit so just one excess code okay so there is no particularly end it
like where one excess is like you will receive an one excess code in front end
of the back end or in your logs because it is not actually an end state it is an
ongoing story to the state it happened at a network layer whenever you are
making a request and between till you receive the response whether it is
success or the failure response that something that is happening on a system
level is like one excess code if system needs any other information between one
of each other that is one excess so the till the moment like let's say you
ordered a food in the restaurant and you are waiting till that food is being
served you are in the one excess code because if you order on a swiggy your
food is being prepared once it is prepared your food is assigned to a
particular driver till it reaches so that status is changing continue
switching protocols or it is you know data is being binded it will be sent
back so all this states right those are on the top level what one excess is
talking about information about the resource is that clear shant
yeah okay I'll discuss this in further if you wanted in doubt session okay no
worries so guys I want you to install a few things how many of you have heard
of visual studio code editor
how many of you installed it how many have you have in this system how many
of you have it I see one thumbs down so I would give you a URL okay so if I open
this let's say I open this URL and also pin this URL okay I've pinned this URL
guys who people who gave me thumbs down you know go on to this size according to
your machine configuration if it is windows or you're using Ubuntu or like
whatever if it is macOS try to install the you know using this website once
you are downloaded we can get started I'll give you five minutes you can do
it install it okay you can like if you go for this one right directly click on
this don't do anything go for the windows part it will download it I don't
need it because my system is not windows okay if you want for a Mac you just go
and click on a Mac it will start the downloading once it is downloaded it
will show automatically installation process click next next next and
download it okay is it fine guys who people who don't have VS code installed
are you trying to do it
okay then there is something called node.js not needed as of now we'll see
them later but at least we if VS code is installed right you what you can do is
you can so let's say open a VS Visual Studio code it would look like this way
like it will go and it will open the you know Visual Studio code and it will show
your recent things and whatever things are there okay so once you reach that
particular place once you are able to download it and open it you can click on
open and open any of the folders that you have anything that you have you can
open it so one thing I'll do is that you know I'll have links in this thing let's
say dot MD inside this file I have this let's say class one inside this I'll
paste this links for your future use case such that if you need it from you
know initial step you will have all these links that you need okay
install editor okay once you do this one MD once markdown that is that's what I
was saying like if I show you in the preview right this is how it will look
like I haven't written anything right like I need underscore or this one if I
write down like let's say one dot I'll show you how we can do markdown or
beautify the documentation part okay but that's just a markdown like you are
trying to describe the country in different way if you do it in double
hash it will show it in different way it's a single hash but I'll teach you
how do you can write a better markdowns also but that's out of the scope guys
okay but now once you are able to install it can we move it guys with your
permission can I move it with the HTML part so I'll go inside the classes I'll
create a class one okay let me create a folder instead of this one I'll go here
inside the classes I'll create a new folder called class one okay inside this
class one I'll create a file called index dot HTML this is a base file that
I'm trying to create it let's say there's a new folder I'll create here
HTML let's push this class one inside the HTML part okay now inside the HTML
right whenever you are writing a structure so there is something like
basic level on a top level as I've told you there is if there is something
taking a birth and then there it should have an end so if you are opening
something this element HTML element you should close this HTML element also is
that clear is that clear that you know every structure of your file will be
enclosed between these two tags when I say tag it is one tag and this is this
is closing tag this is opening tag this is closing tag okay both things are
combined called as an element okay now inside this you know opening and raising
HTML tags well you have two things basically two things now in human one is
structure one is brain right both like brain is someone who is operating whole
body isn't it even though you have too many things like hands legs and eyes and
the mouth speech and everything but something which is driving his brain
isn't it you guys agree with that right similarly here you have two things one
is body okay one is body other thing is head okay head is something which is
not will not be seen by the other end users like users like when I say other
end users I mean to say that something which is running inside my mind you
cannot predict it what is happening but by seeing my body you may see what are
the actions I can make isn't it so whatever you things you write down
inside the body you will be able to see on a website but whatever things you
write in the head you cannot see in the website but are those are the very
important things will explore what all things goes inside head what all things
goes inside the body okay these three elements are clear to you what these
three elements are HTML head and body okay now so what we will start okay let
me write down small definitions also first thing is like how do you add a
comments okay so I what I did is I've did command and forward slash to add
this comment we can type it down manually or you can write down command
slash to get this comment okay or you can do control forward slash for the
Windows laptop so I'll write down small notes also about this one head contains
generally metadata I'll come to this each words later on related to website
there's nothing that you need to get it as of now I'll explain everything step
by step okay now what things are present inside the body is something
that you can see on the screen so whole structure is written inside the body
okay now let's say what if I want to what if I want to write a heading let's
say heading could be I don't want to give a hello world guys can anyone give
me some right heading can anyone give me let's say welcome to scalar okay okay
I've just written welcome to scalar now welcome to world of web anything works
it's just on to it now I've used something called h1 h1 is something when
I say that heading okay so there are two good amount of headings guys that way
you want to write main headings subheading side heading okay all the so
but headings are generally you know from h1 till head 6 you know there are
different types of heading I'll show you let's say I've written h1 and
welcome to scale now since this is rightly you know this is since browser
can understand this HTML directly I should be able to open this file right
the other should be able to understand and show it to me this whole HTML
content right render on the screen that's what we understood when we
understood definition of HTML isn't it
right now let's let's try to do that thing let's try to do that thing okay
give me a second I'll open this
I'm trying to find the okay folder
okay give me a second guys actually I have another desktop where I have all
the files let's say I go back to the browser now if you see here what I am
pasting is the file location in my laptop okay where that file is located
because if you see inside the desktop folder I created full stack merge
because if you see inside the desktop folder I created full stack merge and
classes this is the structure right full stack merge and classes HTML class on an
index system so I'm directly loading the HTML file in the browser I'm hitting
into the browser directly if you see what's happening in the inspect when I
do inspect I go to the network tab when I hit this if you see I made a request I
made a request I made it get request to this system to the file system file
system is also a database right like a local database that's in the present
inside the system it made a call it received 200 status code success status
code and we rendered this welcome to the scalar is this clear guys now directly
the content of HTML is parsed and understood by this browser and loaded
for us is this clear is
okay now second thing is that you know you can also do one thing okay if you go
for this one right marketplace I don't want to load it from always from the
file system server because each time I make a change I have to reload it
refresh it because it will refetch it it will refetch the API and it will load
the data so what I want to do is I want to use a one dummy server on my this one
so in order to create that dummy server I'll go to here in the market list click
this button on your extensions and I try to search with live server okay this
one I'll see if I can copy extension ID and I can give it to you I'm not sure
this is working fine yeah this is the person rithi wiki day is someone who
created you might be able to search with this name also that's something that I
have given okay so say live server I'll write down everything that I'm using
live server extension for loading HTML browser okay yeah I'll pin that give me
a second now what will happen once I do this I go back to the index file now
I'll just right click this one okay and I'll go with open with live server once
I do this okay it is loading in the other instance give me a second let's
say I go back here inside now if you see if you see the URL now what is the URL
this is an IP address of my machine isn't it this is my IP address and this
is a port this is a port where server is running and I'm loading this inside this
port I'm loading this classes HTML index one okay if you see now I got I got three
zero four status code the reason behind I entered this URL if you see I entered
this one it redirected me and loaded the website it does the same thing now what
why I use I'm using this one is as soon as I write down let's say I write down
again h2 since we have all the levels of heading right so I'll say that we are
glad you are here okay if I go and dive down I need not to click anything save
once I click save it is reloaded you know a pay call is being made and you
know loaded for me I hope this point is clear guys so I'll try to introduce all
possible headings for us okay such that we have documented in the notes
whenever someone opens get up I hope this hope you find this you know and
let's say I try to copy paste and create other headings let's say this is h4 this
is h5 h6 h5 h6 h4 okay these are the list of headings we have generally like
if you see this can be a main heading to the page or this can be heading to the
section this can be heading to the paragraph a sub paragraph or the side
all the these are these are the headings given by a given by HTML to us that we
can use it okay now other than headings right we have some other elements that
we will be discussing so I'll introduce one by one okay so most of the you know
most of the website have content to read right content to consume more isn't it
do you guys agree like you go for any site gig for gigs or medium the more
than diagrams more than images it is a more content so to write down content
right the basic one of the main main element that you have is something
called paragraph this is a root element upon this root element each you know
down the lane I'll tell you but frameworks how they have built many
typographies okay now let's say I write down paragraph tag this is paragraph
goes by P later okay once you open and close P so there's something called
lorem guys have anyone knows lorem which generates a content for us
automatically if I am trying to write them lorem this is a Emmett
abbreviation which automatically builds content for me let's say I write down
lorem 35 and then click enter it will build me a paragraph I size of 35 words
okay it's just like I'm trying to generate a dummy data I don't want to
type the whole paragraph okay now if you go and see on the website if you see
this content paragraph is loaded this way okay this is a general size of fan
so whole content is generally written in terms of part now inside this paragraph
you have too many things too many things that you can write down let's say I do
one thing which is called strong which goes for boldness let's say I try to
make here add a strong here okay and I cut this I end it here okay so if you
let's say what how this changes if you see here inside the lorem if I made this
part of it as strong it updated as a bold okay so you might be seeing it
right whenever you want to highlight you go for any document let's say you go for
this document you see there is a color there's inverted comma there is a
change in style okay there will be or maybe somewhere italic or red in color
is a hyperlink okay but what do I you are hopefully you are able to understand
what do I mean to say that it's a paragraph will have a different ways of
showing something which is important content and which is something not right
you go for flipkart if you see open anything anything anything now if you
see everything will have some extra price 60% off 895 striking off now how
do you think this thing can be done in HTML now I don't want you to you know
mug up this even I don't even remember all of them just that you should know
that there's something can be doable and if you are able to search you'll
remember all these stacks only remember important tax and all the other things
we will figure it out okay now imagine that there's something called strike
okay once I do this let's say I go back into the website if you see this part is
striking off the same thing that people are the flipkart team or any other team
have done it so they are striking of this thing and they highlighted the
other thing right bold and striking is that clear how this can be done for the
content paragraph no similarly what people does it right people what people
does it is that you know they also style this kind of thing which they you know
striking off how you can do that thing is let's say you can have another thing
which is italic tag when something if you might have learned in school right
they teach you different types of style writing curse you writing or you know
calligraphy or many things like you bent keywords that you write down because it
goes by bending it to make it look beautiful so that's what happens in
website also once you do this if you see I have striking off I have changed the
style of content okay these are the things that you can do on a content part
okay mainly I've tried to write down four to five things let's say I'll write
down I'll introduce one by one I goes for italics style then strike goes for
scratch over letter words then there's something called underscore also like if
you want to underscore something you can do it using you okay once you do this
let's say I'll show that one also
underline underline sorry underline the words okay if you see I've underlined
this words so this can be done using this way any doubts guys on this part
how we can design a paragraph or how we can style it adding a you know this one
pretty basic and pretty simple and straightforward right now then there is
something called when I introduce hyperlinking right I've talked about
something called links now let's see how can you create a link anyone any guesses
how can you create a link
anyone any guesses there's something called anchor tag
which is used to create hyperlinks now let's say when I define anchor tag
anchor tag goes for a okay a letter now let's say I try to open an anchor tag
okay and inside this I'll say that hey google.com Google search engine okay once
I have this Google search engine here now I've introduced till now I have
introduced till now we talked about elements or the tags now when I say
that this is a hyperlink when I say Google search is a hyperlink when you
click on this it should redirect us to the new website so what we are mean to
say that we are adding some new extra properties or attributes to it now
people are saying there's something called href attribute now what this href
attribute will give us is something where you want it to redirect when you
click it let's say I say that HTTPS double colon WW dot google.com okay so
let's have this thing I save it I go here if you see now this is converted
into blue in color once I had it href now let's say if I click this if you see
here the website made a call to google.com and returned as Google search
engine okay sometimes what happens is where you whenever you open you know
links can we use it is not suggested to it is you cannot use it actually let's
I use href same attribute here that's a it's a wrong thing to do it okay now
even if I click whole thing here nothing is happening okay but if I click this it
is redirecting
clear upendra so each element tag elements will have its own rule so you
have to use them that specifically okay so now you might have seen many things
right if you say that I open this one product it took me to the new page it
didn't open in the new page right does anyone know how to do this when I'm
clicking a page it didn't open me in the same page like when we're clicking this
it is opening us in a same page but we wanted to open in the new like page
right so there is something another you know attribute if I add attribute called
target and underscore blank so it will open in the new blank page target open
in the new blank page okay let's say I go back I open this click on a search
engine just a second it's acha target spelling is wrong okay once I click it
now Google search engine is opening in the new page right I hope you got this
what is anchor tag and how you can handle this clear eyes now other than
hyperlinks or content what do you see else in the website what do you else see
in the website what is the one more important thing
images right now let's say I go for images there is a simple tag call for
images there is a tag called IMG okay to render image now let's see if I write
down IMG there's only one special thing about IMG is that you know it's a
self-closing tag it's a self-closing tag I'll tell you why it is a self-closing
tag as I told earlier that everything which starts it ends it takes it should
whenever I was standing it shouldn't but while writing image you this whatever
content we are writing it we are writing between those tags it is
supposed to be inside that container but image itself is an container you don't
want to write between images right it is on image or behind the image but not
between them you are able to relate this when I write down anchor tag also I
want to write this Google search engine as between this link now added
attributes on over it but images you don't have anything to write between so
there's no use case of having an entire it is itself an ending tag now this
image tag takes two attributes again to show what sort of image it should have
so to in order to show image right if we use something called source tag SRC
SRC is a source or the location of a image where it is located then there is
something called alt alt is something let's say as I've told that HTML is
something a mother tongue to the browser now browsers each mother can have its
own capability right like like let's say Chrome is a very smart mother whereas
Internet Explorer which got deprecated which is very like you know say old age
that doesn't understand all the new things are happening when I say new
things are happening the types of images you have PNG JPEG and everything you
have so there are some browsers which cannot render your certain types of
images you whichever you can cannot read you know render that image you have to
write description for the image what this image is talking about so whatever
you give it an alt something if you are not if that image is not rendering that
alt text whatever you try to text in the alt what that will be rendered onto the
browser okay I hope this is clear so what we'll do is like we'll pick one
images let's say images we'll go to let's say I copy link address copy link
address copy image address sorry okay I go here I give this image address okay
this is way much big my god I did I copy right thing let me go back
let's say what this picture that we copied is about it's an like let's say
lake lake with water and moon okay I have what I've done is like I have
returned a tag image tag with this information I don't know if this image
will work guys let's see yeah if you see I'm able to see a image with the
lake right entering it now if image is not able to render it how can we do
that let's say let's say I don't want I don't give this image description here
let's say I comment this thing okay I cut it okay I cut I cut down the image
now if you see image icon is showing with the lake with a water and moon now
this is how it works that if the images image copyright that that's directly
available if I post it in a public domain Suresh I'll be you know flagged
but I'm not posting pub in on cloud or I'm using or making a business out of
it right until I make a business out of it I'm not you know I can use it yeah we
can use pixels website is it something okay so I hope this is clear guys how
image tag works so these are the least of you know basic tags that you need to
have aware of something to get started with HTML no before ending this class
right I want to add few things okay before ending this class that's something
that I want you to build after once we learn right our learn this HTML and you
know CSS part only with HTML and CSS part I've built one project called
portfolio project I'll share a code base with you I'll also parallel record so
this is something a dummy you know what we say portfolio project which you can
create with only simple HTML and CSS so where you have like you know download
resume button doesn't happen anything it just renders the images and the project
like my project section get in touch form and adding this icons and you know
making this boxes okay all these things can be done using simple HTML CSS so
what I want you guys to focus on is currently till we are in the part of
HTML you want you need to focus on more on the content part like maybe this icon
image home about project section this one then this content part okay you have
to focus on the content part nothing else okay what I'll do is that I'll pin
this link here along with that I'll also keep it here okay at the end of the CSS
class right at the end of the CSS class what I'll do is that I'll also give you
the whole project repo this repo portfolio project repo code such that
you can explore back does that work guys okay yeah great so other than this thing
let's say inside this right I'll create another section called projects okay
let's say not here but
I'll pull it later on projects whatever projects we are building along with that
I'll also create this project basic HTML with you so that whatever time see so
the clock is at 2 11 do you want me to build this projects getting started with
it or you want to build it initially and how you want me to go with
guys do you want me to code it down start with it a simple HTML content for
this one initially okay yeah sure so let's say I have created a project
section I'll create a portfolio project portfolio okay so anyways I have to
provide you the images and icons which you can use it index dot HTML okay now
yeah one message I've got is from Dhanda says someone who knows the language can
we start it on HTML CSS someone who knows the language then as I didn't get
your question when you and you say that language which language you mean to say
that you mean to say coding languages like JavaScript Java maybe we can
discuss about this under in a doubt session I'll get started with project you
know here so there's one shortcut I'll use guys whenever you know there's
something called Emmet when I drive down this HTML right as I've shown you for
the lorem right lorem 35 I've created a content as such you have also you can
generate a dummy HTML okay dummy HTML I'll click HTML I'll find and I'll do it
just click it so I'm able to generate default content now I'll also explain
one thing I forgot to include is that you know here inside the head I didn't
have anything if you go to the website that we rendered it right if you hover
over it that's I go and hover over this tab it is still showing me that same you
know this IP address and port number right what if we want to change and give
it a name like let's say I go to the scalar and I hover it there is no IP
address is being shown or anything it shows that home scalar Academy okay I'll
come to that around give me a minute so inside and head if you want to override
what you want to show on a browser tab right you have a you know tag called
title inside a title you can say introduction to HTML elements okay
HTML since we discussed about attributes to now if I go back if you
see my name got changed okay does it matter to does it matter to any website
it doesn't matter to any website but it's present in head to make it give a
content like what this website is upward okay website is mainly this part but
this is something in the present in head which is not useful okay but that's how
head works the content that you write in heads that's how it works no so someone
asked me what is what is with that HTML file so HTML file introduced few more
things for us like how can you write in HTML in a better way okay for writing
content right for division dividing the content earlier now let's say if I
typed on let's say I want to build portfolio section okay if you see in
portfolio I have basically what all things I have here I'll talk about this
are on in five minutes in portfolio I have something called header right let's
say something I have header okay then there is something called I also have
footer where I have the form okay
then we have my project section then you have a bot me section let's say header
footer my project then also you have a bot me
section so what I did is like I divided our project into four parts to you know
break down what we say you go for DSA big problems think it in the brute
force I'm trying to go with a brute force logic now earlier before HTML 5
right before HTML 5 for dividing any containers right you have something
called diff tax okay each container will have its own diff okay okay so each
container will have its own day there is just a basic like you can say that it's
an structure like sections if you want to do build it in sections you can use
this dev tax okay we will be using this diff tax up to extend that when we are
building projects together okay now inside this diff tax all the elements
that will go is something that we have discussed till now okay let's say if I
want to say that let's ignore ignore this firstly image but here we are having
four things like home a board projects and blog right now let's say if I want
to clear a quick create this one I'll again use our diff tag let's say I
create a home again I copy and paste it okay now let's say I home a book
projects and blog okay so let's have divide done this now I go and back and
open this thing okay live server now let's say I got this four things no what
happened is like we need all of them in one row right what we need all of them
in one row so there is something called span we will I'll introduce this divine
span in next class okay don't worry about this much I'm currently so in
general what I'm what I'm saying is that by adding a span is on a top level is
that I'm I'm telling it a home and a board projects whatever space you need
it use that but don't get started on the new line okay now if you see I'm
getting started on the same line okay so currently while I'm building a
project as of now I'm just focusing on the content part now then I have
something my name let's say I go for the if you see on the top level section I
have only this thing along with that image I'll go to the next section where
I have my name and I'm the full friend full slide developer let's say I go back
on our website where we are coding it okay let's say I use h3 I am Sharma
then I use let's say h5 I am friend and full stack developer okay so what I did
is that if you see I folk went there and I build this content whatever I need so
I'm just focusing on what are the content and now I have a description and
a download resume okay now let me add this part to you give me a second yes
okay now let's say I have a description let's say I for writing a description
right I'll introduce head six I say description then under this you can
write a whole description about yourself and you can also have a ability to give
a button now this is a button okay no let's say I write a paragraph itself be
now let's say for the download resume
whatever we have introduced okay this is what I've covered about first two parts
isn't it like this is something that we have here home about project blog and
this thing in our image now for adding an image also what you can do in this
part you also have an image so let's say I have an image right SRC can be
anything this is all is like let's say profile pic picture for portfolio right
you have written all this stuff simple pretty basic I'm just asking you to
focus on the content part of it since only what we have learnt not going into
further now what happened with HTML 5 is that let's say now I have this thing now
the dips are like if I remove this comments right if I remove this comment
would you be able to understand the structure how it is there how it has
been segregated what is header or about me section or my project footer it would
be difficult right it would be difficult like to see hey what this section is
about to write it down to write it down and understand in a better way what this
people in HTML 5 they have done it is that hey if you are having an header
right in order to tell that it's a header you can write down it as a header
tag itself they introduced new tags now this tax are self-understanding other
than using div everywhere their self-understanding it is helpful to
understand it so this is what they say that semantic tags if anyone asked you
about semantic tags semantic tags are something where you can by default
understand let's say semantic goes by name and it overrides divine span okay
replaces okay now since these buttons are nav bar related item so for nav bar
you can write down nav buttons let's say I can have nap
okay still if I go back and see on the screen it is still same the content got
you know on this way but it is still doing that same job for us isn't it do
you see do you see this guys HTML is not changing anything it just that naming
convention is changing now if you see this section about me now there's
another tag called section which is helpful to you know to know that hey
this is a section separate section this is a separate section so whenever I use
this naming convention right by naming convention even for the button right you
don't use paragraph P tag you have button tag which is introduced in HTML
file so all the semantic tax right all the semantic tags by default whenever
you're using a tag which is understanding by name itself we are
setting we're seeing that header this is a footer tag so I'll use a footer tag
directly not this something else okay so if you go and understand just let's say
that what are the semantic tags definition HTML file is a version yes so
if you see semantic tags are the form stable article where a non semantic
elements are the defense man tells nothing about it contain but it clearly
defines its content like header nab section footer wherever you are using a
name right a name for all the divide divisions or the things that you are
using by default we are saying that semantic this is one of the interview
question also semantic elements are the elements with a meaning hope you'll
remember this case right
okay so so this is where actually I want to you know end the class for today
since we are already on the time and I've started bit on a project section
not going into depth because once we learn this maybe we can build step by
step okay once I complete tables and forms in next class I'll build whole
structure for this one okay we'll build whole the structure for this one then
we'll see on the CSS part step by step works guys good so coming back to this
one guys like give me a I want five minutes of your time I want your five
minutes of time since I landed 230 so one thing one thing I want to tell you
guys is that you know I want everyone might have already you know they might
have their own goals this year like 2024 you might been targeting good job or you
might have taken some resolutions right since this is just a start of an year
okay my job is to help you understand a whole full stack curriculum or in the
books in the part of curriculum of curriculum anything if I don't think I
learn and come back and teach you because it's a vice versa vice versa
learning right because that's my job what I do at office if I don't know
anything I'll come back learn and teach you back but what I want from you guys
is that only three things one of three things is something that attend classes
please try to attend classes such that because most of the content will be
thought and you can avoid the time where you can go and you know watch the
recording but that time can be utilized in a further other things okay second
thing is you know complete your assignments
reason I'm telling you reason I'm telling you why you want to why you need
to complete these assignments is if you do those core problems right and there
with you I will be here if you don't have any you have problems with the
assignment problems initial five minutes of the class right or the other doubt
session will pick those assignment problems will solve them together
works is because that will help you to understand what are the interview
specific things are there and how we can work on it third thing is what I
will do right in the here in the project section in the links right I'll also
have the self study links content where you can read a particular website or
things related to it okay anything I'll give those links do self study utilize
them and read through it just like you know skim through it like whenever you
have five ten minutes of time in a day because I'll have a repo I'll share it
with you repo and you know whatsapp group in that group also whatsapp group
also I'll pin that get up repo you open that get up repo go to the link section
you'll open that hyperlink whatever class has completed that you can just go
through it understand it it would be really helpful for you it's kind of a
revision on a day-to-day wherever you are there five minutes ten minutes not
more than that if you don't understand anything next class I'm there again we'll
discuss it okay and another thing last thing is
contest this thing will it come at last later time but since you have started
this year I want you know this five months the five months that are going to
spend with me just focus on doing the things that I'm asking you to do you
will yourself will see the results at the end of the time okay how confident
you will become in terms of web development okay so hang in there just
do this and one more thing is that a bonus from me is someone who will be
able to do these things right who someone who will be able to do these
things till till like you know react part I'll personally you know mentor them
and refer them at my team in paper okay for front-end or full stack rules but I
want someone to focus on it someone to learn these things okay it is just I'm
trying to create an incentive because everyone here is for their job to up
skill themselves so hope you do all of these things prepare it come back to me
we'll discuss if you have anything drop me directly in whatsapp chat okay so I'll
start a doubt session guys okay and I'll create a whatsapp group give me a second
so I hope you will be able to do all of these things right whatever I needed from
you I've I'll do my commitment job whatever things needed I'll learn I'll
come back to you teach you we'll do the revision stuff if you need an extra
classes we'll think about it but you please focus on attending classes
completing assignments and self-study utilize the links okay I'll keep
updating you something related to if you need to go through anything or anything
but this five months give your attention I know you might have issues like
attitude maybe you want to revise the DSA you want to revise sequel all those
things are important but when you go into the job this will matter more but I
feel it those will clear interviews this will also help you clear interviews
but this is something day-to-day job will revolve around so clearing this
basics I didn't I don't mean to say that completely spend time here but
clearing this basics will help you really you know be confident about the
skill that you are writing down in your resume okay guys so give me a second so
I had yeah thank you Munesh you stock time line on the top of the file
without it what will happen yes it is coming back to that I'll take this so
Suresh has a one question like what will happen if I do or what what this doc
type is about talk type HTML so you know if it if you don't write the stock type
okay if you don't write this doc type there is something you know engines
mother tongues also have a certain way of understanding it okay each browser is
a coded in a different languages and different ways doc type is a keyword
which is explaining it that hey use this particular type of parser in general
okay when we say that this is a document type of HTML it will pass in a
particular way but if you don't write it down this thing this use a different
okay this uses a different quick small now meta tags I introduce in the next
session some bit okay I'll take that in the top first no first question I'll
pick it up meta tax okay in general doc type is talking about is like this is a
document HTML document type so this is that works okay if I google and show you
right doc type okay it's a declaration to web browser that what version of HTML
is written okay generally we are using this you know HTML5 version but if
you go for something website in a depth right that that is not the right website
I will say that you know web.dev if you go to this site right this is somewhere
you have to read because I'll paste this links all these links where you can
where you need to learn this one this is actually maintained by Google so let's
say go for here if you see here and now the doc type so so doc type so it's a
special like I'll come to the notes here I didn't introduce what notes or
anything generally doc types tell the browser to use a standard mode when it
is trying to parse it or understanding if omitted a browsers will use a
different rendering mode called quick modes so mentioning it helps its help
help it to understand in a better way I hope this answers you Suresh is that
fine no reaction did you understand or not yeah it helps understand browser to
in which type it need to parse that HTML like if you explore this quick mode
right like if it is you know older way how the how it used to convert this
HTML like but if you write this doc type in general whenever if you go for the
other sites right it says that hey if you add a doc type it will pass in a
HTML5 version so it means that only how we want to convert this okay so that
can understand pass and render it on the screen so as you define it in short
term helps browser to understand better that's exactly what what you are what I
was talking about okay cool so give me a second I was creating a group just a
second I'll create it on whatsapp mobile images can act as a hyperlink right like
LinkedIn get images website show yeah that can also give me a second I'll come
to that before that I'll create a whatsapp group before all people leave
you
no give me a second I'll share this link and target here
guys this is the whatsapp link you can join using this give it to everyone who
drop the call such that you know everyone can join images can act as a
hyperlink right like LinkedIn get websites you show how does it work okay
so now let's go to this like I'll go to LinkedIn itself let me this is my I
don't have my ID here give me a second I have to use another browser instance
let's say I click on any link right now this link is being converted now let's
say I go what how can you explore more is something let's say you go here and
you click on a hyperlink this element element selector you click here now if
you see anything right if you see in image tag they added a source element
shunt for yourself itself if you can see on a screen share there is a source
element added now the source element is where it is navigating to if I click
here that is where it is redirecting me to okay each image we can you can have a
source to it yet like even if I go back on my let's say I don't want to do this
but let's do this this is a source tag right image let's let's make it not the
give me a second href it should be href itself I'll check that and I'll get back
to you but there should be a redirection link for sure okay no no no no give me a
second
I didn't load it
I think my server got slow so anyways I'll show you this browser is not
responding is it okay let's say you go and add a href to this one I'll copy
this href okay
nothing is happening here but I'll check that and come back to you some with
alt is not mandatory but it is suggested that you have to add it okay alt is not
mandatory but it it is needed like if you see what happens with this right
there are like only for the text no no how does it work so from web development
point of view right only it's it's not only that you know that websites will be
used by the only people who can see it there are other people who cannot see
this I know screen right they use screen readers sometimes you know your mobile
start reading the screen accessibility right yeah so for accessibility for the
impaired people who cannot see the screen they run that website on a screen
or you know reader screen readers mode so when they're reading through the
screen screen if you don't define what your image is talking about they won't
be able to get the context of it so it's needed that you write down the alt for
that content okay great okay then okay then I think guys that's it for
today I hope I hope you had fun it's a just a beginning a session and we'll
learn a lot okay Suresh says that I'm familiar with Java how it will be
helpful for stack journey Suresh I'm the person who started with Java Java is
really wonderful language where you have object-oriented programming and big
things big things saying we're done but it's just a focusing on server side if
you go back right if you go back five ten years before there was no there was
nothing like you know full stack rule there was nothing like JavaScript being
used it was only a Java stack where you have EJP based applications so you had
a timely based applications right where you also write HTML in Java application
itself if you know that right where Java was throwing for HTML screens itself to
the browser okay Java itself was acting as a full stack application sometime
back but later on what it did is like Java told it hey I'm good with the
backend system I'll build that API's that whatever interfaces role it need to
been taken care that will be done by the front end system Java is really great
backend knowledge back backend language I would say which had a really lot of
lot of amount of openings which has a lot of scope but learning full stack
this JavaScript based stack right will add a more of you know flags to you
work Suresh do you get that so it will be really helpful but if you go back
right time leaf like if I show you
like if you go with the time leaf right what it does it is used to resolve you
know screen HTML screens right as far as I remember yeah if you see you are
writing form and table inside Java right so we are you are actually throwing
HTML screens from Java itself so Java is to do all this works but later on they
say that I'll focus on one thing so there are many solutions that were added
time but as the screens got complicated right as more interactivity came more
of things him came so Java was this timely framework was an accurate right
solution to do it then they went on to build this react and angular or simple
you know Ajax calls all those things we'll see step by step one by one okay
you'll get that so rich thank you some bit thank you Suresh did I miss any
doubt hopefully everyone enjoyed today's class guys it was really great class
okay
yeah okay always able to want to help you guys because that's how you will be
learning right that's what you are here for thank you shake after angular came
react that's a different story on and do I will tell you actually they both are
solving different problems I if I since it's a doubt session if I just want to
say it in a word right react solved only small problem react solved one of the
core problem is when I say that HTML is not a programming language right do you
agree with that Anandu HTML is not a programming language then they wanted
like what if I want to create if you go for a site like flipkart right if you go
for a site like flipkart if you see all the stacks right four five tags like one
two three or six sex they both all have same things same size same things only
the image and the data is changing right do you agree only three items are
changing shop now from top-selling pendels or the image right now imagine if
we had a for loop if we had a for loop and we if we can just pass on the three
information and build boxes for me it would be easier right
so what react react told is that hey why can't we write something which will make
HTML dynamic and easier to build user interfaces so react was solving a
problem which can automate the HTML part along with the coding language so but in
the end right in the end browser is always served HTML only so they return
some yeah code replication becomes less so in a way when you are writing a
react you are writing a logic more than a HTML and CSS okay I'll tell them in
depth when we started I'll explain the problem statements and everything but
you'll get to know about react and angular let's wait for that time guys
okay let's build that intuition by then let's be comfortable with all the you
know jargons that we have before that Dom know what is a dom tree how that
happened how react has solved the problem like if I'm using a coding
language since HTML is something browser depends on to render a screen why you
want to write a logic and why you want to convert it how we are enhancing a
speed so there are too many things we'll come to them step by step okay
but till now I would ask you to just focus on the something that we are learning
will build one after the other that works
okay cool so anything else guys before we end the session I'll I'll what I'll do is
like I'll create a GitHub repo I'll share it with you guys okay
I'll wait for another one two minutes if no doubts I'll close the session for
today guys so thank you for attending today's session hope you saw the
assignments and we meet on you know next class Thursday and there's a few
more things to explore in the HTML part then we'll get started with the CSS
okay let's get started with the CSS okay let's get started with the CSS okay
there are too many interesting things we'll learn in the next class where
we'll also complete a portfolio project up to an extent thank you Muneshwara
good night take care
care
okay examine some with when I told about this client and server right
we talked about how connection is established what mode of connection is
there but if if if waiter is bringing a food
he would bring in some utensils and some plate right
do you agree from kitchen when you order a item he'll bring in some plate and
food right now what would be the right sort of
utensil to bring data from backend to the client
from server to the client is in two ways xml is a older way how it used to be
done but json is something a new way of doing
that same thing these are the two formats
where which were used for the mode of communication
when we when there is a mode of communication between the two systems
how data should be transferred so earlier we used to use xml now we
are using json and but xml used in different ways to
write configuration like in many languages like java if you
go for any applications right like spring
application they used to write xml coding to xml
this configuration to explain like what what all things they are using it
but from our learning perspective we'll never see that
from our learning perspective what we'll see is that more of a
json data that is being transferred from backend to the client
instead of json you can also use xml data is that clear because from client
side we can consume both json and xml data
okay so like if you can go to the browser also
xml versus json you can search this okay
you can find it like how these are used this is aws
related you know questionnaire
so it's about like when to use which one how data is transferred over it you can
read about this like you have any doubts while reading
about this you can come back with and discuss you can paste it in group also
what's a group i'll i'll i'll try to answer there also
okay
so otherwise then
thank you shan
thank you sam
so good night guys then i'll stop the screen share
meet you in the next class have a great night
take care
good night shade good night somewhere
okay
i'll have a 10 count 10 second counter and then i close the class
you